George Carroll Papers
Marist College
George Carroll Papers
1943 - 1981
The George Carroll papers consist mainly of correspondence between George Carroll and Lowell Thomas. Additionally, the George Carroll papers include newspaper clippings regarding Lowell Thomas; a president’s report to the Overseas Club; a two-part magazine article on Lowell Thomas written by George Carroll for SKI magazine; photographs of Lowell Thomas, Fran Thomas, and Lowell Thomas, Jr.; Christmas cards from the Thomas family to the Carroll family which include photographs of Lowell Thomas and other family members; postcards from Lowell Thomas; a cartoon drawing depicting Lowell Thomas; a campaign flyer for Lowell Thomas, Jr.’s, political aspirations; the funeral service program for Lowell Thomas; a detailed personal biography contributed by George Carroll’s daughter, Kathleen Carroll; and other miscellaneous memorabilia.
3 linear feet
Carroll, George
Marist College Archives & Special Collections James A. Cannavino Library 3399 North Road Poughkeepsie, NY 12601
No Restrictions. Individuals requesting reproductions expressly assume the responsibility for compliance with all pertinent provisions of the Copyright Act, 17 U.S.C. ss101 et seq. Patrons further agree to indemnify and hold harmless the Marist College Archives & Special Collections and its staff in connection with any disputes arising from the Copyright Act, over the reproduction of material at the request of patrons. For more information please visit the following website: http://www.loc.gov/copyright/title17/.
George Matthew Kevin Carroll was born in Galena, Illinois, in 1900. As a young boy, Carroll moved to Chicago with his family but continued to spend his summers in Galena working in his uncle’s general store. In 1915, Carroll worked as an office boy for Dr. Frederick A. Cook, a part-time mountaineer, who claimed that he was the first person to set foot on the North Pole—not Admiral Robert E. Peary. Dr. Cook wrote a book about his feat entitled, “My Attainment of the Pole,” and gave Carroll a signed copy as a parting gift. While visiting with his brother in Montana, Carroll was inspired by his experiences with riding on cattle trains and meeting real-life cowboys. He wrote a poem about two cowboys under the pseudonym of Bitterroot Bill (bitterroot is the state flower of Montana) and submitted it to the Sunday literary supplement of the Chicago Tribune for publication. The poem, “In Some Far Land,” was published in 1922. With favorable acceptance of his poems, Carroll began writing and publishing poems under his own name. In 1924, Carroll joined the staff of the Chicago Tribune, where he formed lasting friendships with some of the paper’s legendary editors, reporters, and cartoonists. In 1928, Carroll moved to New York where he became the assistant to the promotion manager of Liberty magazine. Here, too, Carroll had the privilege of meeting legendary writers and actors, including Orson Welles. In 1934, Carroll was hired to develop promotional material for the Lake Placid Club, a private resort nestled in the Adirondack Mountains and founded by Melvil Dewey, the inventor of the Dewey Decimal System for libraries. Lake Placid had hosted the 1932 Winter Olympic Games thanks to the efforts of Dewey’s son, Godfrey. Carroll became so successful at promoting skiing in Lake Placid that the Encyclopedia Britannica asked him to write the section on winter sports. Part of Carroll’s job was to play host to the club’s guests and to arrange lectures and film programs. Over the years, those guests included Robert Frost, William L. Shirer, Gene Tunney, and Lowell Thomas, who became an active member of the Club and made the trip with his family to Lake Placid annually. So began years of correspondence between Thomas and Carroll, who not only had to provide snow reports, but also had to work closely with Thomas’s agent and other members of Thomas’s team to make it possible for the radio commentator to do his broadcasts from the Music Room of the Club. In later years, Thomas insisted upon writing the introduction to Carroll’s book about Lake Placid. Carroll and Thomas would continue to exchange funny, revealing letters until Thomas’s passing. Both men shared a fascination with film-making. With Carroll’s encouragement, Thomas agreed to show the extraordinary film he made with his son, Lowell Jr., about their historic trip to Tibet to meet the then 13-year-old Dali Lama. The film was successfully shown in the Agora Theatre of the Lake Placid Club. Carroll, who eventually became Vice President of the Lake Placid Club, would go on to become a member of the Lake Placid Olympic Committee, which helped to bring the 1980 Winter Games to Lake Placid, and to be named to the Lake Placid Hall of Fame. George Carroll passed away in 1993.
George Carroll
The George Carroll papers consist mainly of correspondence between George Carroll and Lowell Thomas. Additionally, the George Carroll papers include newspaper clippings regarding Lowell Thomas; a president’s report to the Overseas Club; a two-part magazine article on Lowell Thomas written by George Carroll for SKI magazine; photographs of Lowell Thomas, Fran Thomas, and Lowell Thomas, Jr.; Christmas cards from the Thomas family to the Carroll family which include photographs of Lowell Thomas and other family members; postcards from Lowell Thomas; a cartoon drawing depicting Lowell Thomas; a campaign flyer for Lowell Thomas, Jr.’s, political aspirations; the funeral service program for Lowell Thomas; a detailed personal biography contributed by George Carroll’s daughter, Kathleen Carroll; and other miscellaneous memorabilia.
- George Carroll Papers, 1943 - 1981
  - Correspondence, 1943 - 1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1960 - 2012 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1952 - 1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - President's Report to Overseas Club, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - SKI Magazine Article (2 parts), February, 1957 - March, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Christmas Cards, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Postcards, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous Memorabilia, 1956 - 1981 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Detailed Personal Biography Contributed by Kathleen Carroll, March, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 10)